software engineering radio episode 96
interview with Christoph charnetski
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se radio
prints irrelevant and detailed
discussions and interviews on soft
engineering topics every ten days thanks
to our audience and the partners listed
on our web site for supporting the hot
rod
[Music]
welcome this nurse to yet another
episode of software engineering radio
this is the long awaited Trotsky
interview many people have requested it
before we get to the actual content let
me remind you that we have our seu radio
get together open space conference in
autumn actually on October 16th and 17th
it's by putting Germany the deadline for
submitting the little small position
papers that we want you to write is
coming up we already received some so
please go ahead
send us the stuff and we'll be looking
forward to meeting you there okay so
much for the for the administrative
stuff let's go ahead with today's
content once again we read ja this year
at in Aarhus Denmark and we have another
interview this time it's with with
Kristoff charnetski I hope the I
probably butchered the first name as
usual so gosh off please introduce
yourself and maybe tell people how to
pronounce your first name correctly
thanks for the introduction I'm
Christoph Jeanette ski and actually
proper pronunciation will be Christoph
charnetski it's a Polish name with a lot
of consonants in it if you know how to
read polish it's easy otherwise just
stick to Christoph okay so I guess
several people well most people probably
know you actually we had a couple of
explicit requests for an interview with
you in our recent listener survey so
you're kind of the thing you're known
for is basically generative programming
so why don't you give us a little
definition of what this is all about and
maybe distinguish it from generic
because some people mix that up as we
learn today so the whole idea of
generative programming is probably best
explained by comparing it to generic or
generic programming if you look up the
dictionary if you look up the word
generic it essentially tells you that
it's descriptive it's a concept about
being descriptive of a
family of things concepts and generative
adds something to it it's about being
procreative well the knowledge of how to
instantiate or create instances of those
concepts so it's it adds this notion of
automation on top of just having highly
configurable components which would be
generic you wrote this book called
generative programming the black book
with a white paper cat on it so most
people I guess know that or if they know
you then it's this book from which they
know you so this book has been I think
it was published in 2000 so what do you
think how did the field evolve what do
you think about all those you know model
development dsm domain-specific visual
modeling MDA all that stuff first of all
I should say that it was a collaborative
effort with absolutely and at the time
when we started working on it I was
actually at the dimer
Ben's later democracy Research Center in
ohm at the very beginning I was still
working on my PhD thesis actually just
about one year into my PhD thesis in
1996 and really originally he was my
supervisor from the Daimler side
industrial part yes but he he actually
he left so he was like supervising my
Master's project and then he left just
after I started doing PhD and and at
that time we actually at the company we
were looking at things like components
and component repositories how to do
reuse how to find components in those
repositories how to classify things and
it was interesting that after all he
left
Daimler he went to the University of
Heidelberg I think the Applied Sciences
University of Heidelberg we still kept
in contact and one day we had a call and
instead of asking you
what would add interesting topics that
we could work on and was interesting
that we kind of both resonated on the
idea that it somehow just storing
concrete components in repositories and
trying to find them it's it's kind of
comparable to needle in a stack and
trying to find it that the right way
would be to have those components kind
of created on demand from some kind of
knowledge about how those components
should solve a particular problem and a
specification of the component yeah I
think there are two common
misconceptions about the book one is
generative programming equals template
metaprogramming I kind of think it maybe
in retrospect you maybe think you
shouldn't have emphasized the template
stuff so much because many people got
put off by that because they thought
that's kind of the same thing would you
agree or is that what do you say about
that I mean first of all before kind of
working on this stuff that ended up in
the book my experience was more with
small talk and I was actually who
dragged me into C++ but then playing
with templates was quite a bit of fun
and one of the interesting things was
sort of was more about discovery what
what's all possible with templates and
seeing that you can actually put some
smartness into libraries Emma in terms
of using those capabilities to do
automatic configuration and there are a
lot of quite practical useful things you
can do of it although it's very easy to
abuse and the reason why we took this
for our examples was just because it was
an off-the-shelf technology it worked
without special tools and it just
demonstrated that a language can
actually support meta programming
although perhaps it wasn't designed to
do so but we just exploded at one
example right another thing you kind of
publicized quite a bit with the book was
the idea of future modeling for very
variability analysis that's a concept
that's known from product line
engineering so how do you see the
relationship between product line
engineering on the one hand side and a
generative programming stuff
on the other side is it the same thing
in some sense well so as I mentioned to
sort of we started with our issues with
components and reuse and so on in fact a
lot of the things that went into the
book and into those ideas originated
from the area of software use domain
analysis in fact at some point this
concept of software product lines came
and was essentially kind of a
reinvention of the area of reuse the
area the field reinvented itself in a
form that made it much more close to
what companies were interested in by
bringing in more than just technical
issues by bringing in the fact that
product lines thinks that in the end of
interest to customers and also the
managers and business issues
organizationally issues have to be taken
into account so in a sense we started
with all of that and we looked at how
those techniques that allow you to look
at a domain and analyze it and see what
concepts you have how to scope it how
this could be used in a systematic way
to then go on and and create for example
libraries that give you the main
specific languages and code generators
is just one technique to implement it
yeah and you know since we sort of tried
to put it all together into a holistic
software development approach we call
the book generative programming rather
than giant of software development just
to sort of say and focus the attention
that this actually is about something
where working code is coming out yeah
and it's very often what happens with
any kind of new technique but the book
is actually covering the whole set of
you know requirements and and
architecture and implementation issues
and feature modeling is just one of the
important ways to look at variability
requirements that's why it was part of
it yeah in in previous episodes we
talked about future models and product
line stuff recently you've been talking
about cardinality based feature models
can you briefly update our
nurse what this is all about so for
example in the book at some point we
were sort of looking and I think wasn't
chapter 4 when the chapter 4 describes
feature modeling and there the form of
feature modeling described is a very
simple one where you when you just talk
about features and that did a mandatory
optional and then they can be
alternative for well inclusive or but
essentially you say what if feature is
there or not but you never have like
multiple instances where a feature fair
and when you look at a system sort of at
a very high level at the level of
requirements very often it's enough to
sort of just say what properties the
system will have in terms of the absence
or presence of a property and not very
often you have to talk about that you
have several instances of some concept
or some feature this rather happens when
you start moving closer to architecture
and to the runtime code of a system so
for example when you start talking about
components and so on you have to think
about how many instances you have of
them and how they are connected in
future modeling actually can be used at
any level whether it's requirements or
or whether it's design architecture and
even close to code and once you move
there you kind of require to use
cardinalities and that something was
actually not in the book yeah but
realized later that it's it's a useful
thing okay let's again briefly come back
to these other acronyms if I talk about
model term development they always say
MDA is a special kind of the general MDD
approach and I always have a hard time
of kind of classifying generative
programming and MDD which is the more
general case it's clearly which is
historically the one that has been there
first
GP clearly I mean MD D is a term that's
at least in the mainstream five or six
years old
yours is older so how do you see the
relationship between these different
things generative programming DSM well
DSM is just drawing pictures it doesn't
necessarily generate code but the MDD
MDA world
the generative programming growth how do
they will relate so I've been looking at
model driven development for at least
five to six years yeah and there is not
much talk about those terms in the book
because just at that time it wasn't
present in that form however I got
interested in that because surely there
is a lot of commonalities between motor
driven development and the ideas from
generative programming and the things
that I wanted to explore is to see what
has come on what are possible synergies
what are the things that are different
and one thing that I observed ely was
that in in muldoon development has been
but it was in at least in the early days
of it a lot of focus on things like
platform independence so in that sense
supporting variability across different
platforms yeah that's the MDA incredible
thing exactly and without sort of
telling you what does it mean to be
platform specific and this is something
that actually is a sort of a central
theme to domain analysis or to product
lines where you sort of scope a domain
and say well this is my problem domain
this is my solution domain on technology
space and this allows you to sort of
delineate and say well something is in
the it's part of the platform oh it's
part of the solution domain or not and
that depends on a lot of factors
including strategy factors and so on of
a company but at least with domain
analysis you have a systematic way to
talk about that whereas it was
completely absent in the MDA world at
the time yeah later I saw that and and I
guess also worked myself in that area
and and many people like including you
Mark Christie they sort of bring
together the idea of modeling and and
software product lines and you know by
that
definitely very much gets closer to the
spirit of generative programming by
always sort of looking at a domain
trying to make it more operational in
terms of having the knowledge to to
create instances
of concepts in the domain altimeters as
much as possible so in that sense it's
getting very close
still I think there are sort of
disparate I can see still disparate
communities and a lot of potential for
further synergies and integration yeah I
mean that brings me to the point that
I've complained about in previous
episodes already I mean the community
overall is relatively small compared to
other mainstream things and then there
is still 15 different passwords I'm TSM
MD DMD a GP and you can go on software
factories DSL towards I mean it's
basically all the same thing everybody
puts their own spin on it but it's bit
frustrating that the community or the
communities can't agree on a common set
of terms well it's bad and good too in a
sense because if if you have an area
where everyone is agreeing on everything
then the area is probably pretty much
dead it's not advancing very much it's
not an exciting place to be I mean I'm
not saying that people should agree in
all details but you can't even agree on
what bottom model is people don't do
some people call things metamodel of us
call it domain model whereas other call
others call models domain models so it's
completely confusing it's not about you
know harmonization of the approach the
ideas but a couple of basic terms at
least that would be helpful I absolutely
agree
I guess those things just take time and
so I make sure for example when I give a
talk to define actually very much try to
avoid the use to use the word meta they
often you just it's enough the same
model and you have to just make sure
that you define all the words are using
I'm not sure you can do more than that
no probably not
okay so I don't know I don't remember
did you actually say what you do these
days where you work that you're a
professor did you say that in your intro
no I didn't okay just okay no problem so
so that brings me to the point that
you're actually doing research today so
what's the kind of stuff you
working on today as I said kind of I
wanted to explore first the relationship
between management of programming and
modern development and sort of that
pushed me into looking at a lot of the
things that exist in the modeling world
and so on and one of the interesting
problems there is is the question of
what is the language to represent models
and domain-specific languages is
certainly a concept that is quite
important in joint of programming and an
increasingly important in multi-room
development any question is where do we
take those domain-specific languages how
do we come up with them how do we
develop them systematically and I've
been working in this area for quite a
while and sort of maybe a number of
years after moving to well I moved to
Waterloo five years ago and up to it
about two years ago I was I was looking
at modeling at Fairleigh requirements
level but my problem at some point was
it was very difficult to evaluate the
work see whether it actually brings
value or not because there's just simply
not it's a catch-22 problem there's
simply not enough models being use out
there that you could use this as a way
to scientifically study yeah
the practices and and and try out detect
your techniques so I sort of also wanted
to have models where something running
comes out so that sort of moved me to
look into models that closer to
architectures closer to frameworks
closer to code and then sort of the
question how you can get those modeling
languages there in this context and work
with them and that's that sort of the
topic of my work today for example how
do you create the main specific
languages from api's of platforms and
frameworks in the MDD world people have
always been saying that TS ELLs and
modeling languages and frameworks are
two sides of the same coin that if you
have dsl from which you generate code
and then there is always this framework
against which you generate so what you
do is you go the other way around you
say there is a framework now how can we
find the language that describes well a
framework
I recall this instance a configuration
or program that uses the framework
correctly okay it's less correct correct
so so mushy I made the key idea is to
sort of look at the API and say well the
API provides you with some concepts that
you for example is a application
programmer will instantiate in your
application code and and allow you to to
create applications but very often those
concepts are just not explicit in your
code
scattered entangled across the whole
codebase and making that explicit that's
where DSL come in but you can also see
it sort of the other way around and say
that by creating frameworks and
improving them evolving them you sort of
grow the DSL in an incremental way so
that means that then that that the model
is relatively close to the code in some
sense it's not like you have a rectangle
that becomes a class but there is a
direct relationship between what the
model describes and what the code does
how it does it what code looks like so
this probably allows you to do some kind
of round-trip engineering I guess maybe
I hope yes it's true the models are not
as close to the code as you would say
that they're just a simple rendering of
the code yeah the idea is to really show
the concepts that frameworks provide and
in a certain sense you would say like if
you have a application that has a clear
architecture where you have multiple
instances of some domain concepts by
baking the api's that provisos concepts
explicit you can actually start creating
those dsls and then having models that
show you those instances in the
application so it's actually if you have
an architecture clear architecture to
your application you can you can use
those languages to show the elements in
the vocabulary of the architecture also
to check rules whether these are the
architectural constraints have been
followed and so on and even the
roundtrip engineering in that case the
language represents in some sense the
capability of your framework now that
kind of contrasts with some of the other
approaches well the MDA on paper and
maybe intentional in practice where you
say you actually analyze what what goes
on in your domain
which is way more that's a
business-oriented as opposed to
technology oriented so so that kind of
conflicts or how do you how do you
position you there it's too different
it's not it's not a conflict it's just
two different approaches that can
naturally coexist so in a sense when you
look at what dsls can come from like I
can I can sort of think of three sources
one being essentially the domain experts
already knowing exactly what they're
doing and just observing it and they
typically already have a language and a
TSL can just make it explicit and it's
it's an example of example from
intentional software using the insurance
policy rules and the business people
seems pleased in that one case are quite
happy with how they can now describe the
products in the policy workbench yeah
there are many example other examples
where you have a well-defined area of
expertise with much your practices where
you can just come in and essentially
harvest the existing language another
source of T cells are essentially
well-established theories about a
particular problem area state machines
state machines for example so MATLAB
Simulink with with its block diagrams
that essentially represents sets of
differential equations those theories
tend to give you a language that is kind
of computationally complete and and
fairly universal you know that any kind
of system in that domain can be
described and there's sort of no fear
that your domain
well the main specific language is not
mature another example it is recently so
as a language I think it's called flicks
it's a colleague of mine at the
University of Waterloo
professor cash off he has a language for
describing network routers and he worked
out first sort of he did domain analysis
of the problem he worked out
former semantics of the problem with
fixed point semantics and then came up
with a language is extremely beautiful
and was demonstrated and actually you
can see it just from the abstractions
that it can describe any kind of routing
problem and most of the existing
protocols they try to describe already
and it seems to be working very well
however there is still a lot of problems
out there where simply as a developer
you don't know exactly the concepts of
the domain you don't even know what the
domain boundary is you have to adapt
because the requirements are changing so
the only way you can do is try to build
some kind of working model and often you
do it with a programming language and
try to distill some abstractions out of
it well that's you do it typically using
some creating some libraries of
frameworks and gradually you grow this
set of abstractions and then you create
applications in top of it by instantiate
in those things and that's where it
would this approach of framework
specific modeling languages are putting
the modeling languages on but the ESL's
on top of framework comes in let's look
at an example in the slides i looked at
to prepare you know we always prepare
for interviews more or less there was
this nice example with the Eclipse
framework so why don't you give our
listeners a little bit of concrete
example of what such a model would
describe for example in the context of
Eclipse editor parts so people can
understand more specifically what it's
all about you're referring to this
example by the way I should mention that
this is PhD work of one of my students
behind kovitch an excellent researcher
and designer and developer and so on
yeah I know him so so this particular
example so he's developed a language for
looking at the code of a Eclipse plugin
and understanding what workbench parts
of elements such as editors outline
views and property views are
instantiated in the code and how they
interact in terms of high-level
interaction saying for example what kind
of events such as selection events or
part activation activation events are
being sent
between those parts and in Dakota it's
normally not so easy to see in in order
to have in a interaction such as sending
the selection events you have to
register the parts with appropriate
framework services if to implement
appropriate interfaces you have to write
methods that return appropriate
specialized objects like adapters and so
on yeah so in a sense something that is
maybe relatively a crisp concept in
someone who is thinking about the
architecture of the plugin that there is
a certain kinds of events being
exchanged is actually not so easy to
find in the code yeah so the particular
sample language that he developed makes
this explicit and it allows you to
retrieve those things from from plaquing
code and also allows you to do roundtrip
engineering between those this kind of
models and the code so that the model
contains things like a workspace part
has to implement that isn't that
interface well--there's to send this
event you have to call those methods
this is the meta model and the models
just says what what are the things that
are being done so in that sense the
metamodel just basically it's a set of
concepts such as those parts and
interactions with features as properties
of those concepts representing those
implementation steps if you like the
developers would have to do in order to
get this concept to work you said that
in kind of as a relative sentence you
said that you can actually extract a
model from the code so the model isn't
you it's not your primary artifact you
extract the model from the code you
change it and then can you reapply the
changes to the existing code base I
guess exactly so so here's a very
specific assumption that there's enough
information in the code to retrieve the
model at any time I want and that just
works for code and the kind of models
that sort of rely that there are certain
patterns such as for example patterns of
the usage of the API and very often
frameworks have a certain set of
patterns how the API should be used yeah
so it's it's if you like it's it's it's
the specific architecture rules of the
platform of the framework that allow
to retrieve those models right and so
it's a very specific kinds of models but
they're still nevertheless useful
because they tell you about what
components you have in your app in your
code and whether they follow various
architectural rules and so on what we
talked about now was to basically
predefined the language the metamodel
manually and then extract an instance
from an existing piece of sample code so
that's and then then resynchronize it
back yes where's the resynchronization
it's it's still not a non-trivial thing
you have to essentially transfer
transform the existing code to make it
consistent with the model and I guess
you do that on ast level Eclipse
excellent okay but but you talked about
another thing and that is actually
automatically extracting the language so
you get do you give the system a bunch
of example in this case editor parts or
whatever and the system automatically
extracts the configuration space the
variability the language that you need
to describe it
yes that's relatively new focus on my
students like taking as a direction with
the idea that the the patterns of usage
of those concepts provided by the
frameworks but they can be actually
looked up in existing applications and
we've got with open source lots of
examples out there typically yeah and
you can use this to sort of understand
how the frameworks ApS are actually
being used by developers and you can
mine rules sort of like saying yeah if
I'm implementing this class or this
subclass in this class or implement this
interface also have to make those in
those calls and out of those rules you
can actually synthesize those domain
models metamodels representing the API
rules and in that sense this gives you
also a certain adaptivity in a sense
that as new patterns emerge you can
actually propose new new kind of
abstractions to sort of take care of
those new patterns and say well you know
we automate them now because now we have
an abstraction or intentional eyes them
if you like
right mark exactly so in that sense it
allows you to sort of grow the language
and the whole idea is that the language
will never I mean in in this this
context here we just sort of say that
there are situations where you don't
have a language that covers all the
variability points and all the choices
and all the alternatives that you would
like to have and so it's it's it's
automatically its kind of partial
whether it's a DSL that sits on top on
top of another DSL or code doesn't
matter it's it's just automating certain
kinds of patterns that you would have to
type in in the other language so just to
re-emphasize the fact that you're doing
this on code and API level it's not
necessarily the only application you can
take basically if you come up with a
meta model people use it build models if
a bunch of models then you analyze those
models with those rules and then take
this this as an input for evolution of
the metamodel a common stuff we'll be
right into the language exactly and I
could start with any level grow the
language to be more mature and I'm once
I'm using that language I could start
introducing high level abstractions yes
because once we have a high level model
I mean our software this development
trade has this property that whenever we
have new tools that allow us to manage
certain level of complexity way we just
quickly go to the next level yet this is
actually really an interesting spin to
actually mine language use in order to
come up with ways of how to improve it
very nice okay first off I think that
that that brings us to the end of what
we prepared thank you very much for
being on the show and well hope to see
maybe at some point another book that
kind of maybe updates some of the things
you have been thinking about that and
maybe the important project these days
is my two-year-old son and I'm still
trying to cut down on my commitments
reddit yeah but who knows I was actually
surprised that that actually happened
with specifically with you because
known as a quite a bit of a workaholic I
guess so I'm working in it okay thank
you very much
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
SE - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
by on the website or you can advertise
for se radio for example by clicking on
the dick reddit delicious and /not
buttons to contact the team lists an
email to team and SI radio net or if
it's specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can read and react to your
comments this episode of software
engineering radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under Creative
Commons license please see the website
for details thanks to Charlie crowd and
the pot site Music Network for the music
used in this show the song is called
Vegas hard rock shuffle
[Music]